Guide to the Henry De Bourbel Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Henry de Bourbel papers
1791-1814
OSB MSS 102
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.33
(2 boxes)
Correspondence, legal papers, and financial papers documenting Henry de Bourbel's business affairs while he was an émigré in England, in particular his finances relating to Senecé & Roumare. Correspondents include Bernard de Senecé, Bourbel's partner in Senecé & Roumare, Charles Des Essars, who purchased his share in the firm, and Richard Watts, an attorney who helped negotiate the settlement of a debt owed to Jean François. Legal papers include articles of association and dissolution for Senecé & Roumare and insurance policies on shipments from London to Bremen aboard the ships Patriot, Rebecca, and Sophia. Financial papers prior to the dissolution of Senecé & Roumare in 1797 include bills for various merchandise and legal services and receipts for bills of lading. Later financial papers consist of receipts and accounts of Bourbel's debts, in particular the debt owed Jean François. Family papers consist of an acte de brevet issued by Jean Dominique de La Rochefoucauld, Cardinal of Rouen, for the erection of a chapel and a receipt for a fine on families of émigrés paid by Louis de Bourbel, Henry's father.
Bourbel, Henry de, comte de Montpinçon, 1770-1826
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Julian Browning on the Hazel M. Osborn Fund, 2000.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
HENRY DE BOURBEL (1770-1826)
Henry de Bourbel, Comte de Montpiçon, was born Antione Raoul Henri de Bourbel in Dieppe, France, in 1770. Bourbel moved to England in 1790, renting a plot of land from the family of Luke Spence, Malling Place, Lewes, Sussex.
Bourbel relocated to London, where in 1794 he entered into a jewelry and coal trading partnership with Bernard de Senecé under the name Senecé & Roumare. On February 2, 1795 he married Mary Ann Spence, grand-daughter of Luke Spence, at St. Anne Soho in London. Bourbel's partnership with Senecé was dissolved in December 1797 when he sold his share to Charles Des Essars.
Bourbel left London for Lewes after dissolving his partnership with Senecé, but did not complete the settlement of his debts with Senecé and Des Essars until 1801. Richard Watts, a lawyer and steward of the Spence family estate, helped Bourbel negotiate with Senecé and Des Essars. Bourbel returned to France with his family in 1801.
Henry de Bourbel and his wife had three children, Henri Alonzo de Bourbel (October 26, 1799-1821), Auguste Harold de Bourbel (January 30, 1804-ca. 1845), and Caroline Aurelia de Bourbel (1807-?). He died in Paris, February 21, 1826.
Scope and Contents
The Henry de Bourbel Papers consist of correspondence, legal documents, financial papers, and family papers related to Henry de Bourbel, a French émigré in England during the French Revolution, and span the years 1791-1814. The papers are housed in 2 boxes (including 1 oversize box) and have been organized into four series: Correspondence, Legal Papers, Financial Papers, and Family Papers.
Series I, Correspondence, is arranged alphabetically by correspondent in folders 1-44. The bulk of the correspondence is letters to Henry de Bourbel, but it also contains three letters written by Bourbel and a few third party letters.
The correspondence is almost entirely related to business matters, especially regarding Bourbel's credits and debts following the dissolution of Senecé & Roumare. Major correspondents include Bernard de Senecé, Charles Des Essars, Richard Watts, and J. W. Cooke.
Correspondence filed under Senecé & Co. includes letters from both Senecé and his partner Des Essars. Their correspondence begins after the dissolution of Senecé & Roumare, and primarily relates to settling debts with Bourbel, who had been bought out by Des Essars. Their letters are written in French.
Richard Watts was a lawyer and steward of the Spence family estate. His correspondence concerns debts that he helped Bourbel negotiate, in particular a debt owed to Jean François, who left a sum of money in the hands of Senecé & Roumare in 1795.
J. W. Cooke was a London merchant who wrote to Bourbel concerning a purchase of farm machinery. One of his letters, Aug 27, 1800, includes a printed list of "Cooke's Newly Invented and Greatly Improved Patent Implements and Machines."
Unidentified correspondence includes summaries of Bourbel's accounts with various merchants, including Senecé and Des Essars.
Series II, Legal Papers, is arranged chronologically in folders 45-47, and 65-70 (oversize), and consists of documents related to Henry de Bourbel's business interests, including articles of association and dissolution for Senecé & Roumare, insurance policies on voyages taken by the ships Rebecca, Patriot, and Sophia, declarations of trust between Hartsinck & Co. and Henry de Bourbel, a power of attorney for Charles Des Essars, and an agreement regarding debts.
Series III, Financial Papers, is arranged chronologically in folders 48-62, and 71 (oversize). Financial papers from 1795-1797, during which Henry de Bourbel was an active partner in Senecé & Roumare in London, consist of bills and receipts for various merchandise, receipts for bills of lading for the ships Rebecca, Patriot and Sophia, and bills for legal services from William Stacey and Moses Hoper. Merchandise purchased by Bourbel included household furniture, locks, silk cloth, gold plate, rice, scissors, cork screws, tweezers, and pen knives.
Financial papers from 1798-1801, after Bourbel left London, consist of accounts and receipts, most of which relate to the settling of debts between Bourbel, Senecé, and Des Essars, including a debt owed to Jean François. Undated financial papers include two itemized receipts for the purchase of household furniture and supplies.
Series IV, Family Papers, consists of two items in folders 63-64. The first is an acte de brevet issued by Jean Dominique de La Rochefoucauld, Cardinal of Rouen, March 31, 1791, giving permission for the erection of a chapel on the estate of Henry de Bourbel's grandfather, Emmanuel Raoul Antoine de Bourbel (1708-1787). The second is a receipt, May 23, 1796, for a fine levied on the families of émigrés paid by "Citizen Bourbel of Heugleville," Louis de Bourbel, Henry de Bourbel's father.
Debtor and creditor -- Great Britain; Trading companies -- England -- London; France -- History -- Revolution, 1789-1799 -- Refugees; Great Britain -- Commerce; London (England) -- Commerce; Bourbel, Henry de, comte de Montpinçon, 1770-1826; Bourbel, Louis de, 1732-1814; Des Essars, Charles; François, Jean-Marie, 1752-1826; La Rochefoucauld, Jean-Dominique de, 1931-2011; Senecé, Bernard de; Watts, Richard, attorney; Patriot (Ship); Rebecca (Ship); Senecé & Roumare; Sophia (Ship)
- Correspondence, 1796-1814; Series I; 44
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Correspondence, is arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  - Baker, Richard
    - 2 ALS to Henry de Bourbel, Lewes, Sussex, 1800 Aug 16-19 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bourbel, Henry de
    - ALS to Francis Goold, 1797 Nov 18 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Includes Francis Goold receipt to Henry de Bourbel on verso, 1800 Jul 31
    - ALS to William Stacey, London, 1798 Jun 10 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - ALS to Charles Cressy, 1801 May 30 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Brown, Thomas Pearce
    - ALS to Richard Watts, Whetstone, 1801 Sep 9 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Cooke, J. W.
    - 7 ALS to Henry de Bourbel, Lewes, Sussex, 1800-1801 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
  - Cressy, Charles
    - ALS to Henry de Bourbel, Lewes, Sussex, 1800 Jun 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - De Gougon
    - 3 ALS to Henry de Bourbel, London, 1797 Apr (Box 1, Folder 9)
      In French
  - Des Essars, Charles
    Related Archival Materials note
    See: Senecé & Co., Box 1, folder 22-33
  - Fery, John
    - ALS to Ransom Morland & Co., 1796 Sep 13 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Fyffe, William
    - ALS to Senecé & Roumare, London, 1798 Feb 19 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Goold, Francis
    - 2 ALS to Henry de Bourbel, 1799-1800 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      See also: Bourbel, Henry de to Francis Goold, 1797 Nov 18, Box 1, folder 2
  - Gotobed, Browns, & Gotobed
    - ALS to Henry de Bourbel, Lewes, Sussex, 1801 Aug 5 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Hoper, Moses
    - ALS to Henry de Bourbel, Lewes, Sussex, 1800 Jan 10 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Johann Carl Weinhardt & Co.
    - ALS to unknown third party regarding debt to Senecé & Roumare, 1797 Aug 23 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Lamy
    - ALS to Henry de Bourbel, 1798 Apr 30 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - La Rocque, M. de (André Jean)
    - ALS to Henry de Bourbel, 1796 Dec 21 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      Includes a copy of a letter from De la Rocque to Dulare Libraire, 1796 Dec 21. In French
  - Marinais, Jospeh Louis
    - ALS to Henry de Bourbel, London, 1797 Nov 7 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Nodin, Frederick Shore
    - 3 ALS to Henry de Bourbel, Lewes, Sussex, 1799-1800 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Pracointal
    - ALS to Henry de Bourbel, 1796 Jul 3 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Ransom Morland & Co.
    - ALS to Henry de Bourbel, Lewes, 1800 Jul 31 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Senecé, Bernard de
  - Senecé & Co.
    44 letters from Bernard de Senecé and partner Charles Des Essars to Henry de Bourbel, Lewes, Sussex. Includes letters written by Senecé and Des Essars both together and separately. The bulk of the correspondence is from Des Essars. In French
    - 1 ALS and 1 AL, 1797 Dec 1-19 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - 20 ALS and 12 AL, 1798 Feb-Nov (Box 1, Folder 23-30)
    - 7 ALS and 1 AL, 1799 Jun-Dec (Box 1, Folder 31-32)
    - 2 ALS, 1800-1801 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Spinola, Marquis de
    - AL to Henry de Bourbel, 1796 May 26 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Stacey, William
    - 4 ALS to Henry de Bourbel, Lewes, Sussex, 1798-1799 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Tabé
    - 3 ALS to Henry de Bourbel, Lewes, Sussex, 1800 Jul-Aug (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Thomas Martin & Co.
    - ALS to [Henry de Bourbel?], 1814 Sep 10 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Watts, Richard
    - 12 ALS to Henry de Bourbel, Lewes, Sussex, 1800-1801 (Box 1, Folder 38-40)
      2 letters include itemized accounts of Watts's legal services
  - Unidentified
    - Note relating to James Harcombe and [Joseph?] Marinais, 1797 Sep 7 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Summary of business between Henry de Bourbel and Senecé & Co., [ca. 1798 Sep] (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Summary of business with several merchants, [ca. 1798 Dec] (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Summary of miscellaneous business transactions, [ca. 1799 Jul] (Box 1, Folder 44)
- Legal Papers, 1794-1798; Series II; 9
  Series II, Legal Papers, is arranged chronologically.
  - Articles of association between Senecé and Bourbel, 1794 Nov 15 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Ransom Morland and Co. insurance policy on voyage of the ship Rebecca from London to Bremen for Henry de Bourbel, 1796 Jan 19
  - Ransom Morland and Co. insurance policy on voyage of the ship Patriot from London to Bremen for Roumau & Co., 1796 Nov 23
  - Ransom Morland and Co. insurance policy on voyage of the ship Sophia from London to Bremen for James Boydell, 1797 May 12
  - Declaration of trust between Hartsinck & Co. and Henry de Bourbel, 1797 May 17
  - Declaration of trust between Hartsinck & Co. and Henry de Bourbel, 1797 Jun 24
  - Deed of dissolution for Bourbel, Des Essars, and Senecé, 1797 Dec 22
  - Power of attorney from Charles Des Essars to Richard Hannam and William Stacey, 1797 Dec 22 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Agreement between Senecé and Bourbel and Charles Cresy and John Ashley regarding debts, 1798 Feb 10 (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Financial Papers, 1795-1801; Series III; 16
  Series III, Financial Papers, is arranged chronologically.
  - Receipts, 1795 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Account of Henry de Bourbel with William Wennington, 1796 Jan 15
  - Receipts, 1796 Jan (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Receipts, 1796 Mar (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Receipt of John Drinkard, 1796 Sep 7 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Accounts and receipts, 1796 Nov (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Bill from William Stacey for work in the Court of Common Pleas, 1796 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Receipts, 1797 May (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Bill from William Stacey for legal work involving Henry de Bourbel, Francis Goold, and Col. Edward Dillon, 1797 Jun (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Receipts, 1797 Sep-Oct (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Accounts and receipts, 1797 Dec (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Account between Henry de Bourbel and Senecé and Des Essars, 1798 May 25 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Receipts, 1798 May (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Receipt of Francis Goold, 1798 Jul 7 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Accounts and receipts, 1801 Jun-Aug (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Accounts and receipts (Box 1, Folder 62)
- Family Papers, 1791-1796; Series IV; 2
  Series IV, Family Papers, is arranged chronologically.
  - Acte de brevet issued by Jean Dominique de La Rochefoucauld, Cardinal of Rouen, for erection of a chapel, 1791 Mar 31 (Box 1, Folder 63)
    In Latin
  - Receipt for payment by [Louis de Bourbel], of fine imposed on families of émigrés, [1796 May 23] (Box 1, Folder 64)
- Oversize, 7; (1 box)
  - Ransom Morland and Co. insurance policy on the ship Rebecca (in Series II), 1796 Jan 19 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 65)
  - Ransom Morland and Co. insurance policy on the ship Patriot (in Series II), 1796 Nov 23 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 66)
  - Ransom Morland and Co. insurance policy on the ship Sophia (in Series II), 1797 May 12 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 67)
  - Declaration of trust between Hartsinck & Co. and Bourbel (in Series II), 1797 May 17 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 68)
  - Declaration of trust between Hartsinck & Co. and Bourbel (in Series II), 1797 Jun 24 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 69)
  - Deed of dissolution for Bourbel, Des Essars, and Senecé (in Series II), 1797 Dec 22 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 70)
  - Account of Henry de Bourbel with William Wennington (in Series III), 1796 Jan 15 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 71)